A Guide to the Letters of North Carolina families, 1813-1914 (bulk 1813-1896)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Letters of North Carolina families 1813-1914 (bulk 1813-1896)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
1030
100 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased by the Library from Paul Ashburn of McKee Pontiac Company, Washington, D. C., on January 8, 1941.
Scope and Content
This collection contains 100 letters, 1813-1896 and 1914, dealing with a wide variety of issues, including family life, agriculture, slavery, finances, religion, education, and politics, especially in North Carolina, but also in South Carolina, Alabama, Georgia, Kentucky, Tennessee, Ohio, Florida, Maryland, and Pennsylvania.
The three chief areas of North Carolina represented are: Salem, Forsyth County; Germantown, Stokes County; and, Huntsville, Surry County. For more on Stokes and Forsyth counties and their histories and families, please see the two editions of Forsyth, A County on the March (The University of North Carolina Press: Chapel Hill), 1949, by Adelaide Fries, and 1976, by Adelaide Fries, Stuart Thurman Wright, and J. Edwin Hendricks, contributors. The following are excerpts from the 1976 edition's chapter entitled "The Formation of Forsyth County and the Founding of Winston":
The story of Richmond Town was dramatic and short, for the 1789 Surry County was divided by a north-south line, and new courthouse sites were selected--Rockford in Surry County and Germanton in Stokes County. The Surry County courthouse records were removed from old Richmond to Rockford; Stokes County set up new records on her own account. The area now called Forsyth was mostly in the new county of Stokes, but straight lines were still the custom, and the new line crossed and recrossed the Yadkin in an annoying fashion. As a result, Stokes had a long narrow strip west of the river on the Surry side; Surry had a C-shaped tract east of the river in the part of Rowan which became Davie County. In each case these detached pieces could be reached only by boat, for there were no bridges.
In December 1796 the assembly changed the line between Surry and Stokes, giving to Surry the long narrow strip lying on the west side of the Yadkin, the river becoming the boundary there. The Act of Assembly calls in the land "south of the Yadkin," but old deeds show that for many years everything on the righthand bank of the Yadkin River, looking downstream, was called "south" of the Yadkin, regardless of the actual direction.
For fifty years the county of Stokes remained practically unchanged. The War of 1812 and the Mexican War made but slight demand upon the people, though the former called the attention of the nation to Colonel Benjamin Forsyth. The population increased slowly, but it did increase, and finally the General Assembly of 1848-1849 was petitioned to divide it. The act dividing Stokes County bears the ratification date 16 January 1849, and it printed in full in the Laws of the State of North Carolina passed by the General Assembly at the Session of 1848-1849, published at Raleigh in 1849 by Thomas J. Lemay, Printer, Star Office.
The act provided for a line "beginning at the South West corner of Rockingham county, and running thence West to the Surry county line." It was further enacted "that all that part of the said county lying North of said line, shall be erected into a distinct county by the name of Stokes county; and all that part lying South of the said line shall be erected into another distinct county by the name of Forsyth county, in honor of the memory of Northern frontier, in the late war with England." A supplemental act, passed at the same session of the assembly, appointed Caleb Jones, Frederick Meinung, and John Banner to run the dividing line, named county commissioners for each county, and provided the necessary machinery for setting up the two county governments. The commissioners for Forsyth County were Zadock Stafford, John Stafford, Henry A. Lemly, Leonard Conrad, and Francis Fries, who was elected chairman.
After the formation of the new county and the naming of her commissioners, it became necessary to select and purchase a site for the county seat; a courthouse and public building had to be erected as soon as possible. Because Salem was located almost at the center of Forsyth, it seemed apparent to the commissioners that they would have to choose land in that neighborhood.
Papers of Forsyth County are chiefly concerned with the Van Vleck and related Blickensderfer and Fries families, and describe life, religion, and education in Salem, Forsyth County (formerly in Stokes County), North Carolina; Dover, Ohio; and Bethlehem and Nazareth, Pennsylvania. Information on the inhabitants of the county and its history may be found in the multi-volumed Records of the Moravians in North Carolina, particularly Volumes IX (1838-1847) and X (1841-1851). Each volume contains its own index of persons and places. There are numerous mentions of Francis [nee Franz Levin] Fries during the years 1838-1851, with a detailed record, 1848, of his requests to build cotton and woolen mills as well as buildings and additions, and land transactions; and, there are several mentions of Arthur Van Vleck during 1849-1850. Correspondence of the widow of Carl A. Van Vleck, Christina Susanna (Kramsch) Van Vleck, and her children, Amelia Adelaide, Arthur Lawrence, Lisetta Maria, and Louisa Cornelia, discusses family, education, religion, travel, and the mission service during 1849 of Arthur. According to the Moravian Records, in 1846 an appointment was offered to Arthur Van Vleck in Greeneville, Tennessee, to serve as teacher at Nazareth Hall, [Pennsylvania]; the family arrived in Salem on the following fifteenth. Records for 1849 indicate that the Wachovia Provincial Helfer Conferenz in Salem recommended Arthur Lawrence Van Vleck for service in a mission school; and, in April 1849 he was called to serve as assistant missionary and assistant teacher at Saron on Barbadoes. In 1850, the records report:
...that the mission conference in Barbadoes had unanimously expressed this opinion, that the Single Br. Arthur L. Van Vleck was not suited for mission service, for which reason the U. A. C. had advised his return to North America. It further commends him both to the P. H. C. at this place and to the Pennsylvania P. H. C. for employment as a home missionary or in some other way.
The P. H. C. at this place wholeheartedly regrets that the attempt to place Br. Arthur Van Vleck in the West Indies has failed but considers itself unable to use him in the congregations of this district or in our home missionary undertaking.
There are several letters, 1848-1852, from Francis Fries to his wife Lizetta (Vogler) Fries, from areas in South Carolina and North Carolina; these are chiefly personal.
Francis Fries (17 October 1812 - 1 August 1863) was descended from an old German family, which in the eighteenth century turned from war and court life to trade. His grandfather, Peter Konrad Fries, studied theology at Strasbourg and received his Ph.D. in 1741; in 1758 he joined the Unitas Fratrum (Moravian Church), later becoming a member of the Unity's Elders' Conference and holding important posts in this religious fellowship. His paternal grandmother was Christiane Jaschke, the daughter of a Moravian exile. His father, John William Fries, after receiving a Moravian education in Europe, came to the United States and settled in the Moravian colony of Wachovia (later Salem), where he married Elizabeth Nissen. Although his parents wished for Francis to become a minister and sent him to the Moravian seminary, Nazareth Hall, Pennsylvania, he decided against the ministry. After returning home, he taught for a while and then read law with Emanuel Shober and entered practice, soon being appointed clerk of the court and master in equity.
Fries' business career began when as agent of the new Salem [cotton] Manufacturing Company, he visited Paterson, New Jersey, and other northern points to purchase machinery, which in 1836 he installed in a factory building erected after his own plans. In 1838 [May 24] he married Lizetta Vogler, by whom he had seven children [including Caroline Louise, John William, and Mary Elisabeth]. Two years later, with the assistance of his father-in-law, he commenced woolen manufacture; at first he operated only cards for making rolls of the wool brought in by farmers, and set up a little dyeing and fulling mill for finishing cloth woven in the homes of the countryside. Being successful in these enterprises, in 1842 he installed spinning machinery, and then looms. He was encouraged in manufacturing by his friend Edwin M. Holt of Alamance, with whom he made arrangements to make alternate information-gathering trips to the North to study developments in the older textile centers, afterward sharing their information. The South manufactured very little at this time, but the tradition of the Moravians in North Carolina was one of mechanical enterprise, and Fries did more than any one else to foster this spirit. His brother, Henry W. Fries, was taken into partnership in 1846; two years later they built a cotton factory which was conducted until 1880, when it was dismantled and became part of the woolen mill.
Fries was involved in other endeavors. As a member of the legislature in 1857 he gave special attention to revising the state system of taxation. He was an architect, who designed the court-house for the new county of Forsyth and the main building for the Salem Female Academy, of which institution he was a principal supporter. He was also mayor of Salem. He was a promotor of the plank road from Fayetteville to western North Carolina and was associated with Governor John M. Morehead in building the North Carolina Railroad, in which he was a director until his death. Fries built a tannery, conducted a store, and was one in a small but important group which sought vainly to implant industry in the agricultural ante-bellum South. [from the Dictionary of American Biography, Volume VII (Charles Scribner's Sons: New York), 1931]
Papers of Stokes County contain chiefly letters addressed to Hampton Bynum from John H. Farmer in Bowling Green and Russellville, Kentucky, and others. Farmer writes of financial matters and land purchases and settlements in Kentucky. There is also a letter from John Gray Bynum, Columbia, South Carolina, concerning the selling of slaves and personal finance issues of this attorney. There are also two letters from C. M. Pepper to his father, John Pepper, concerning his education in Emory and the literary society (9 April 1851), and his preaching circuit and religion (25 May 1853). Letters, 1843-1849, addressed to John Hill (9 April 1797 - 24 April 1861), Clerk of Stokes County Court, concern financial matters; and, a request, July 2, 1849, from John A[dams] Gilmer (4 November 1805 - 14 May 1868), state senator, for a female prisoner, Jane Hill, to be given the right to take the "insolvent debtor's oath."
The letters of Huntsville, Surry County, North Carolina, are chiefly from Isaac Jarratt in various cities in Alabama, to his wife, Harriet A. Jarratt. These letters contain personal content from a husband to his wife as well as advice and/or news of the family "negroes" and farm, and life in Alabama.
Papers of other counties of North Carolina include a variety of correspondents and topics. An interesting letter of May 30, 1838, was written by George D. Phillips, Clarksville, Georgia, to Maj. Thomas B. Cooper, Jefferson, Cherokee County, Alabama, concerning the escapades of a slave named "George," trouble between Indians and U. S. troops, and frost damage to crops. There is also an interesting letter, November 1, 1841, from Elijah [ ], Yazoo County, to Andrew McCants, Union Post Office, Georgia, describing travels through Mississippi, western Tennessee, Arkansas, and Louisiana, with a lively discussion of the city of New Orleans. There is a letter, June 28, 1865, from H[enry] P[arker] Sartwell (18 April 1792 - 15 November 1867), physician and botanist, writing about impending botany publications by prominent botanists.
Contents List
- Series I: Salem, Forsyth County, North Carolina
  - Benjamin G. Walz, Baltimore, Maryland, to Rev. [William Henry] Van Vleck, Minister of the Moravian Congregation: [letter in German]. 1836 Sep 21
    [William Henry Van Vleck (14 November 1790 - 19 January 1953) of Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, was a Moravian Bishop]
  - American Tract Society to Theodore Schulz, Salem, Stokes County, North Carolina: religious publications. 1837 Apr 21
  - American Tract Society to John Vogler, Treasurer, Tract Society, Salem, Stokes County, North Carolina: religious publications. 1837 Aug 3
  - E[dmund] S[amuel] Zevely, near Middleburg, Loudoun County, Virginia, to J[ohanna] Sophia Zevely, Salem, Stokes County, North Carolina: personal and family news; the family farm in Charlotte, North Carolina. 1845 Sep 13
  - Cordelia [Levers?], Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, to Lisetta M[aria] Van Vleck, Greeneville, Green County, Tennessee: personal news. 1845 Oct 15
  - Louisa [C. Blickensderfer], Dover, Ohio, to Lisetta Maria Van Vleck: description of travel to Zoar, Bolivar, Ports Station, and Tuscarawas River, Ohio; history of the "Indian Dancing Ground," personal and family issues. 1846 Jul 15
  - [C. D.] Williams, Greeneville, Tennessee, to Louisa C[ornelia] Van Vleck: medical--bilious attack; news of friends in Greeneville, Tennessee; personal news. 1846 Aug 9
  - L[ouisa] C. B[lickensderfer], "Bignonia," Dover, Ohio, to Lisetta M[aria] Van Vleck: personal and family news; lengthy description of trip to Zoar for Sunday religious meeting of "Pappy" [Joseph Michael] Bimeler (ca. 1778-1853), founder of the community of Zoar. 1846 Nov 10
  - Hannah [ ], "Bignonia," Dover, Ohio, to Louisa [Cornelia] Van Vleck: education, teaching school children at a "select school" at Dover, Ohio. 1847 Jun 26
  - Mary C. Poindexter, to Mrs. C[hristina] S[usanna] Van Vleck: personal and family news; relations in Ireland. 1848 Feb 15
  - F[rancis] Fries, Camden, South Carolina, to Lisette (Vogler) Fries: personal and family news; return trip from Georgia and stay at Col. James Chesnut's. 1848 Jul 4
  - L[ouisa] C. B[lickensderfer], Dover, Ohio, to Lisetta Maria Van Vleck: medical pains; personal and family news. 1848 Dec 15
  - L[ouisa] C. B[lickensderfer], Dover, Ohio, to Lisetta M[aria] Van Vleck: personal and family news; mission life and diplomatic service of Arthur Van Vleck. 1849 Jun 5
  - J[acob] and L[ouisa] C. B[lickensderfer], Dover, Ohio, to Lisetta [Maria] Van Vleck: illness; domestic issues; and family news. 1849 Sep 12
  - [Arthur Van Vleck], Sharon, Pennsylvania, to Mrs. C[hristina] S[usanna] Van Vleck: mission teachers and mission life in Sharon, Pennsylvania; "African character" and the effect of "firmness." 1849 Sep 18
  - [ ], Dover, Ohio, to her sister Mrs. C[hristina] S[usanna] Van Vleck: personal and family news; mission work. 1849 Sep 21
  - Louisa [C. Blickensderfer], Dover, Ohio, to Lisetta Maria Van Vleck: personal and family news; Whig party. 1849 Nov 30
  - C. D. [Williams], Greeneville, Tennessee, to Louisa C[ornelia] Van Vleck: Episcopal Church congregation in Greeneville, Tennessee; personal and family news; marriage of Robert Barton and Hannah McFarland. 1849 Dec 15
  - Jacob Blickensderfer and Louisa [C. Blickensderfer], Dover, Ohio, to Mrs. C[hristina] S[usanna] Van Vleck: Arthur Van Vleck's journey to Bridgetown, Barbadoes; conflict between Postmaster Sandford Shultz and Jacob Blickensderfer. [1849] Dec 24
  - Louisa C. B[lickensderfer], Dover, Ohio, to Amelia A[delaide] Van Vleck: personal and family news; illness and deaths of Charles Blickensderfer; life at "Bignonia," Dover, Ohio. 1850 Jan 18
  - F[rancis] [Fries], Pattonsburg to "Lizzie" [Lizetta (Vogler) Fries]: personal. 1850 Apr 12
  - Harry [ ], Nazareth, Pennsylvania, to Lisetta [Maria] Van Vleck: "wife searching expedition" of Edwin Reinke; work on the new school house in Nazareth, Pennsylvania. 1850 May 7
  - "Letty" [Lisetta Maria Van Vleck?], Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, to "Louisa and Amelia," addressed to Louisa C[ornelia] Van Vleck: travel to Petersburg, Richmond, and Mount Vernon, Virginia, and back to Pennsylvania [with letter of June 5, 1851]. 1850 Jun 12
  - Jacob Blickensderfer, "Bignonia," Dover, Ohio, to Amelia A[delaide] Van Vleck: family life at "Bignonia," Dover, Ohio; personal and family news. 1850 Aug 17
  - F[rancis] Fries, Henderson, North Carolina, to "Dear Lisetta" [Lizetta (Vogler) Fries], addressed to Emma A[ntoinette (Reich)] Vogler: paper mill in Henderson, North Carolina. 1850 Aug 30
  - C[hristina] S[usanna] V[an] V[leck], on Cape Fear River, North Carolina, to "Louisa and Amelia," addressed to Louisa C. Van Vleck: personal and family news. 1851 Jun 5
  - F[rancis] Fries, Salem, North Carolina, to Lisette (Vogler) Fries, City Hotel, Philadelphia: personal and family news. 1851 Jun 15
  - Lisetta [Maria Van Vleck], Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, to "Louisa and Amelia," addressed to Louisa C. Van Vleck: personal and family news; improvements in Bethlehem, Pennsylvania. 1851 Jun 26
  - Henry [W. Fries], Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, to "Louisa," addressed to Mrs. Christina S[usanna] Van Vleck: personal and family news; Arthur Van Vleck's impending return; students being pleased at Nazareth, Pennsylvania. 1851 Aug 20
  - F[rancis] Fries, Raleigh, North Carolina, to Lisette (Vogler) Fries: personal and family news. 1852 Feb 9
  - "Aggie," Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, to Amelia A[delaide] Van Vleck: personal and family news; description of landscape in travels in Fayetteville [ ? ] and Portsmouth [ ? ]. 1853 May 31
  - Louisa C[ornelia] Van Vleck, to Mrs. C[hristina] S. Van Vleck, Bethlehem, Northampton County, Pennsylvania: Bethlehem Female Academy; personal and family news. 1854 Jul-Aug
  - "Aggie," Berthelsdorf, Germany, to Amelia A[delaide] Van Vleck: life in Germany; description of area in Berthelsdorf, Germany; description of young ladies there; education and religion in Germany. 1854 Nov 12
  - M[ ] [Fries?], Salisbury, North Carolina, to parents Mr. and Mrs. H[enry] E. Fries, Winston-Salem, North Carolina: "good looking men...also some flossed up lassies" on their train. 1914 Jun 13
- Series II: Germantown, Stokes County, North Carolina
  - H. and I. McRae and Company, to Mr. R. D. Golding, Germantown, North Carolina: order and account for sundry items. 1833 Jan 13
  - J[ohn] M[cPherson] DeSaussure (1807-1883), Camden, South Carolina, to Hampton Bynum: financial issues; crops, including cotton. 1838 Sep 10
  - John H. Farmer, Bowling Green, Kentucky, to Hampton Bynum: financial. 1838 Oct 6
  - N. G. Martin, Montgomery, Alabama, to Hampton Bynum: cotton not selling because of low river; selling of slaves; banking issues; nomination of [William Henry] Harrison (1773-1841) for President and the Whig party. 1840 Jan 17
  - J[ohn] M[cPherson] DeSaussure, Camden, South Carolina, to Hampton Bynum: family estate settlement. 1840 Feb 3
  - John H. Farmer, Russellville, Kentucky to Hampton Bynum: land purchases in Russellville, Kentucky. 1840 Feb 12
  - John H. Farmer, Russellville, Kentucky to Hampton Bynum: business issues; land purchase in Kentucky. 1841 Feb 20
  - William Collins Joseph, Comptroller, to John Hill, Stokes County, North Carolina: financial statement. 1843 Oct 24
  - J[ohn] M[cPherson] DeSaussure, Camden, South Carolina, to Hampton Bynum: estate settlement. 1844 Apr 8
  - John H. Farmer, Russellville, Kentucky, to Hampton Bynum: personal. 1844 May 5
  - John H. Farmer, Russellville, Kentucky, to Hampton Bynum: financial. 1844 Jun 14
  - John H. Farmer, Russellville, Kentucky, to Hampton Bynum: land settlement near Bowling Green, Kentucky; land and crop prices. 1845 Jul 26
  - James Huske, Fayetteville, North Carolina, to John Hill, Germantown, Stokes County, North Carolina: financial. 1847 Nov 23
  - John Gray Bynum, Columbia, South Carolina, to Hampton Bynum: selling of slaves; financial issues of John Gray Bynum, attorney. 1848 Mar 13
  - R. D. Scales, Aberdeen, Mississippi, to John Hill, Clerk of C[ounty] C[ourt], Germantown, Stokes County, North Carolina 1849 Mar 6
  - John A. Gilmer, Greensboro, North Carolina, to Jailer of Stokes County and John G. Hill, Sheriff, Germantown, North Carolina: requesting that Jane Hill, prisoner be given the right to take the "insolvent debtor's oath." 1849 Jul 2
  - C. M. Pepper, Emory, Virginia, to his father [John Pepper, Germantown, North Carolina]: education in Emory, Virginia; literary society news. 1851 Apr 9
  - C. M. Pepper, "Smithville," to his father John Pepper, Germantown, North Carolina: his preaching circuit and hopes for holding a high position in the [North Carolina] Conference; comments on religion and the Bible; collecting sea shells and curiosities. 1853 May 25
  - B. H. Bynum, [Salisbury & Asheville, North Carolina], to W. H. Bynum: personal and financial news. 1878 Dec 26
  - Wade H. Bynum, Winston, North Carolina, to Mrs. C. H. Bynum: personal. 1883 Sep 7
  - R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Company, Winston, North Carolina, to Wade H. Bynum: taxes on hunting property. 1896 Jan 8
- Series III: Huntsville, Surry County, North Carolina
  - Isaac Jarratt, Montgomery, Alabama, to Harriet A. Jarratt, Quincy, Gadsden County, Florida: daily life in Montgomery, Alabama. 1835 Feb 1
  - Isaac Jarratt, Montgomery, Alabama, to Harriet A. Jarratt: love and dedication of husband to wife and son; selling of slaves; "Sandy"--last negro sold; wanting to bring "Patty" and other negroes home; debts; closing business in Montgomery, Alabama and Florida; Chattahoochee River so low steamboats can't run. 1836 Jan 3
  - Isaac Jarratt, Greensboro, Alabama, to Harriet A. Jarratt: slave prices; "Silvy's" escape and return; advice on obtaining a female negro as a cook; mentions "Mary" and "Flora"; instructions for work on plantation during winter; farming and cotton in Greensboro, Alabama. 1836 Dec 21
  - Isaac Jarratt, Sumter, Alabama, to Harriet A. Jarratt: not letting negroes be idle; "Mary" and "Eliza"; slave prices; trouble with "Hunter." 1838 Mar 9
  - Thomas A. Cash, "Vallencia," Ash County, North Carolina, to Harriet A. Jarratt: personal and family news 1846 Oct 5
  - Mary Smith, Wilmington, North Carolina, to Harriet A. Jarratt: Indian problems in Wilmington; travel to Boston; personal and family news; medical--leeching. 1847 Jun 2
  - M. Gibson, to Harriet A. Jarratt: life in Florida; personal and family news; whooping cough and death among young negroes. 1848 Oct 25
  - Isaac R. Harris, Quincy, [Gadsden County, Florida], to Isaac Jarratt: prices for hiring negroes next year. 1849 Nov 26
  - Mary Smith, Wilmington, North Carolina, to Harriet A. Jarratt: personal and family news; medical--whooping cough and scarlet fever. 1850 May 5
  - Mary Smith, Wilmington, North Carolina, to Harriet A. Jarratt: personal and family news. 1850 Sep 25
  - T[homas] A. Cash, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to "Dear Mother" [Harriet A. Jarratt]: personal and financial issues. 1864 Jan 12
  - Mary Smith, Wilmington, North Carolina, to Harriet A. Jarratt: personal and family news. n.y. Nov 20
- Series IV: North Carolina Counties General, 1813-1849
  - John M. Gordon, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Benjamin James Harris, Richmond, Virginia: power of attorney from John Bullock. 1813 Feb 6
  - H. Potter, Raleigh, North Carolina, to Gen. Samuel Simpson, Fort Barnwill, Craven County, North Carolina: seeking debt payment. 1815 Jan 10
  - James B. Hamilton to Andrew McCants, Union, Talbot County, Georgia: payment on goods. 1835 Jan 2